<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="cage.shift" module="cage" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Insert or delete time at the beginning of a score
	</digest>

	<description>
		Perform a time-wise shift of all the content in a <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o>
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">cageproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">cage</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">cage scores</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Original score
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Shifted score
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="offset" optional="1" type="number">
			<digest>
				Offset
			</digest>
			<description>
				The optional argument sets the shift offset in milliseconds (for <o>bach.roll</o>) or in
				number of measures (for <o>bach.score</o>), or even in the form <b><m>num_measures</m> <m>symbolic_offset</m></b>
				(for <o>bach.score</o>, see message <m>list</m>).
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Output shifted score
			</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs result of the last shift.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set offset
			</digest>
			<description>
				An <m>int</m> in the second inlet sets the time shift amount in milliseconds (for <o>bach.roll</o>)
				or in measures (for <o>bach.score</o>)
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="list">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set offset
			</digest>
			<description>
				A <m>list</m> in the second inlet sets the time shift amount for <o>bach.score</o> in the form
				<b><m>num_measures</m> <m>symbolic_offset</m></b>. For instance, a shift of <b>2 17/8</b> will add 2 empty
				measure at the beginning and then also shift everything by 17/8. The added measures will receive the
				same time signature as the first measure, whereas the further symbolic offset will be simply processed
				without changing time signatures.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				An <m>llll</m> in the first inlet is considered as
				the <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> gathered syntax. The shift
				operation is performed and the modified gathered syntax is output through the outlet.
				The output header content is the same as the input header content. <br />
				An <m>llll</m> in the second inlet is converted to <m>int</m> or <m>list</m> (see corresponding messages)
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message.
				To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format,
				except for the size limitation), some specific kinds of symbols are preceded by a backtick: namely, symbols containing parens, or containing textual
				representations of numbers or pitches, or beginning with a backtick, plus the symbols "null" and "nil" (distinct from the reserved words
				"null" and "nil" representing the empty list and the empty sublist) are preceded by a backtick. Moreover, the symbols "int", "float" or "list"
				are preceded by a backtick only if they are the first element of an llll, to distinguish them from the corresponding reserved messages of Max. <br />
				<m>m</m>: 'max' output: mostly equivalent to the "t" specifier, but no symbol is backticket except "int", "float" and "list" at the beginning of an llll.
				It is important to notice that, differently from text-format lllls proper, Max-format lllls might not be invertible even if they do not reach the size
				limit for Max message. This means that a bach object receiving a Max-format llll output from another bach object might interpret it differently
				from the original, or in some cases might even reject it. <br />
				<m>x</m>: disabled output (nothing is output) <br />
				<m>p</m>: 'portal' output: only used by bach.portal to intercept the @out attribute specified while creating the abstraction (see bach.portal). <br />
				The native output is recommended, unless communication with standard Max messages is needed.
				Disabling unused outputs can be useful if extreme optimization of the patch is needed.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="save" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="cage.rot" />
		<seealso name="cage.rev" />
		<seealso name="cage.inv" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				Original score.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				Shifted score.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>